

□ (+45) 60 90 60 12 | ☑ erik@i-solution.de | 🏕 www.erikkusch.com | 🖫 ErikKusch | 💆 KuschErik | 🛅 Kusch Erik | R° Erik Kusch

Research Profile

I am a macroecologist specialised in remote sensing applications and spatio-temporal analyses. I use quantitative tools to research ecosystem resilience, vegetation dynamics, and patterns of landscape-scale biodiversity to understand past, present, and future trajectories of natural ecosystems. Current work includes identification of species-interaction networks, software development for climate data retrieval and aggregation, and propagation of uncertainty of climatic data into biological analyses.

Education

PhD in Biology; Specialisation on Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity

01/2020 - PRESENT

AARHUS UNIVERSITY (AU) & OXFORD UNIVERSITY (OX)

Primary Advisor: Alejandro Ordonez (AU)

External Supervision: Roberto Salguero-Gómez (OX)

Contents: Climate data practices in biological research

Species interaction inference and network modelling Species extinction and extinction cascade simulations

M.Sc. in Biology; Specialisation on Biodiversity, Ecology and Evolution

08/2017 - 08/2019

University of Bergen (UiB) & Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center (Nansen)

Primary Advisor: Alistair Seddon (UiB) External Supervision: Richard Davy (Nansen)

Thesis: Inferring Vegetation Memory from Remote Sensing Data and identifying Causal Links to Plant Function

B.Sc. in Biology 10/2013 - 07/2017

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD) & UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN (UIB)

Primary Advisor: Alistair Seddon (UiB) Secondary Supervision: Klaus Reinhardt (TUD)

Thesis: Remote Sensing And Predicting Shifts In Biome Distribution And Resilience Using NDVI Data

Specialised Training

7th Edition Species Distribution Modelling Course

Évora, Portugal

University of Évora, Science Retreats

26/04/2021 - 02/05/2021

An Introduction to Bayesian Statistics

Glasgow, Scotland 06/04/2021 - 16/04/2021

University of Glasgow

Modelling Challenges for Mountain Ecosystems

Hamburg, Germany

University of Hamburg

23/02/2020 - 28/02/2020

Plant Functional Traits Course 3

Wayquecha Biological Station, Peru

University of Bergen (UiB), University of Arizona (UoA)

08/03/2018 - 24/03/2018

Bayesian Modelling Summer School

Lygra, Norway

Norwegian University of Life Sciences (NMBU)

25/10/2017 - 29/10/2017

Experience

Research Fellow

Research Station Co-Manager

Scoraig, Scotland

SPATIAL AND POPULATION ECOLOGY, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW

06/2019 - PRESENT

ECOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL CHANGE RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN

Bergen, Norway 09/2019 - 12/2019

National Park Ranger & Environmental Education Guide

Saxony, Germany

NATIONAL PARK SAXON-BOHEMIAN SWISS

04/2016 - 06/2016

Research and Teaching Assistant

BEHAVIOURAL ECOLOGY RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF LEIPZIG

08/2017 - 08/2019; 03/2017 - 04/2017

PRIMATE RESEARCH CENTRE, UNIVERSITY OF KYOTO

07/2018

GERMAN CENTRE FOR MARINE BIODIVERSITY RESEARCH, SENCKENBERG GROUP

05/2017 - 07/2017

Teaching & Supervision Activity

Author & Lecturer: AU Bayes Study Group	Personal Course Web Page
Seminar Series	Official Course Web Page
Author & Lecturer: Excursions into Biostatistics	🕓 Course Web Page
Seminar Series	☐ GitHub Repository
Author & Lecturer: An Introduction to Biostatistics Using R	🔇 Course Web Page
Talk Series	□ GitHub Repository
Author	🔇 Course Web Page
BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH IN THEORY AND PRAXIS (BFTP)	Aarhus University
Teaching Assistant	Aarhus University
Applied Statistics	22/03/2021 - 14/05/2021
STATISTICAL AND GEOSPATIAL MODELLING	03/09/2020 - 18/12/2020
GEOSPATIAL INFORMATION SYSTEMS	27/10/2020 - 18/12/2020
Instructor & Advisor	
ECOINFORMATICS & BIODIVERSITY MASTERS SEMINARS (EBMS), AARHUS UNIVERSITY	03/02/2021 - 05/05/2021

Extracurricular Activity

Group Member

Elected Member: Students Council of Biology Studies at the TUD	Dresden, Germany
EECRG READING GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN	10/2017 - 12/2019
Bayes Study Group, University of Bergen	09/2018 - 12/2019
Spatial Shared-Interest Group, University of Glasgow	10/03/2021 - PRESENT
STATISTICS JOURNAL CLUB, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW	10/03/2021 - PRESENT

08/2017 - 07/2018

Elected Member: Students Council of Biology Studies at the TUD

CENTRE OF EXCELLENCE IN BIODIVERSITY EDUCATION (BIOCEED), UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF DRESDEN 10/2013 - 10/2015

Honours & Grants & Awards

SCHOLARSHIPS & GRANTS

Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students , Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship	Aarhus, Denmark
Funding for Particularly Talented Students, Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond	Bergen, Norway
Fast-Track-Initiative Funding, FTI, Bjerknessenteret	Bergen, Norway
Project Grant, L. Meltzers Høyskolefond	Bergen, Norway
Scholarship , German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes)	Bonn, Germany
	Funding for Particularly Talented Students, Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond Fast-Track-Initiative Funding, FTI, Bjerknessenteret Project Grant, L. Meltzers Høyskolefond

AWARDS

10/2019	Best Poster: Student and Early Career Researcher , International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria
10/2019	Modeller's Choice Poster Award, International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria

NOVEMBER 1, 2021 ERIK KUSCH · CURRICULUM VITAE

KrigR - The R Package	Hamburg, Germany
Speaker, AK Klima Interimstreffen	25/03/2021
KrigR - Downscaling State-of-the-Art Climate Data for Macroecologists	Aarhus, Denmark
Speaker, BIOCHANGE Methods Workshops	12/11/2020
KrigR - Climate Data For Your Spatial Study	
Invited Speaker, SalGo Team, University of Oxford	18/06/2020
Speaker, International Statistical Ecology Conference 2020	25/06/2020
Identifying Ecological-Memory Patterns in Drylands using Remote Sensing	
Invited speaker, Ecosystem Research Group, University of Oxford	15/10/2019
Speaker, International Society for Ecological Modelling Conference 2019	04/10/2019
Invited speaker, Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity Research Group, University of Aarhus	06/09/2019
Spatial Patterns of Plant Performance	Bergen, Norway
Invited speaker, BIO Day,University of Bergen	15/03/2019
Inferring Vegetation Memory from Remote Sensing Data	Glasgow, Scotland
Invited speaker, Spatial Ecology Group, University of Glasgow	09/01/2019
Posters	
Intrinsic vegetation memory as a proxy of engineering resilience may be an oversimplification	
POSTER AUTHOR AND PRESENTER, INTERNATIONAL STATISTICAL ECOLOGY CONFERENCE 2020	25/06/2020
POSTER AUTHOR AND PRESENTER, INTERNATIONAL SOCIETY FOR ECOLOGICAL MODELLING CONFERENCE 2019	03/10/2019
POSTER AUTHOR AND PRESENTER, BJERKNES CENTRE FOR CLIMATE RESEARCH ANNUAL MEETING 2019	16/09/2019
Writing	
Reconciling high resolution climate datasets using KrigR	R _X Preprint
Co-Author Author	2021